History [music] isn't just what
happened.
[music] It's what still matters.
[music] The decisions,
the turning points, the stories that
shape our present.
This is history told [music] forward.
conversations that looked back
to better understand [music]
what comes next.
Today's guest is a man who lived on the
front lines of intelligence, integrity,
and [music] consequence. John Kiryaku
spent 15 years with the CIA. First as a
Middle East analyst and later as a
counterterrorism operative who led
operations in hotspots like Pakistan in
the years after 9/11. But it wasn't just
his time in the field that made
headlines. It was his courage to speak
out. In 2007, John became the first US
official to confirm and publicly
denounce the CIA's use of waterboarding,
a move that cost him his career, his
pension, and his freedom. He was charged
under the Espionage Act and served 2
years in federal prison, becoming a
prominent [music] whistleblower in the
post 911 era. Since then, he's become an
author, journalist, and fierce advocate
for transparency, [music] ethics in
government, and the rights of
whistleblowers. His story is one of
sacrifice, resilience, and an [music]
unwavering commitment to truth. Please
welcome John Curyaku. John, why don't we
start a little bit? Give everybody a
little bit of a a background.
>> Sure. I uh I spent uh 15 years in the
CIA. Uh the first half of my career in
Middle Eastern analysis, the second half
in counterterrorism operations. Uh I
blew the whistle on the CIA's torture
program, which came back to bite me
later. But before it bit me, I uh went
on to be the chief investigator on the
Senate Foreign Relations Committee. And
then uh the Obama administration fell on
my head, charged me with five felonies
for going public about the CIA's torture
program. Did two years in prison. And um
since getting out, I've become an
author, journalist, commentator,
whatever you want to call me. I've got a
bunch of books and I'm kind of
entrepreneurial.
So, uh a little bit here, a little bit
there and you can put together a living.
>> Yeah, absolutely. This this episode is
going to be kind of dear to me because
uh um when I was in and and overseas,
you know, I spent 68 months total
between Bosnia, Iraq, Afghanistan, and
>> garden spots.
>> Yeah. The the awesome places, [laughter]
but um you know, I really developed a
hatred for for the people. I didn't
really even look at them as people. And
uh since I've been podcasting and and
learned a little bit more about PTSD and
and trauma and so forth, it has opened
up uh some uh rabbit holes that that I
have gone down. You know, one like does
the people that we fought, do they have
PTSD? Is there somebody over there that
is struggling like we do as Americans?
And as I've learned, so are is the
Australian forces, the the British
forces. they've all been on my show and
and they've all talked about it as well.
So, I I've looked at things a little bit
different and it's made me reook at the
the Marine situation at their prison
camp and and the things that they were
doing and uh you know, they're just
Geneva Convention is is a tough issue
for us to deal with. It it does kind of
handicap if you're following the rules
when you're fighting other people that
don't play by rules. However,
um you lose a little bit of your soul if
you don't follow it with either. So, I
think this episode's going to be great
to get into it. So, so let's let's dig
into this a little bit. Let's start out
with
>> what uh what brought you to the uh the
CIA? I mean, how did that come about?
>> Well, it's kind of a funny story. When I
was 9 years old, I told my parents that
I wanted to be a spy when I grew up. And
the only the only knowledge I had about
spying came from Mad Magazine from Spy
Versus Spy, you know, seriously.
>> Okay.
>> And then then when I was 16, I told my
dad specifically that I wanted to be a
spy in the Middle East. I was fascinated
by the Middle East as a kid.
>> Wow. And then when I was in grad school,
my grad school adviser turned out to be
a CIA officer undercover as an academic
and he uh recruited me into the CIA. And
so I started on um Iraq. Uh I was the
Iraq leadership analyst and um I had a
degree in Middle Eastern studies. I had
a master's degree in in legislative
affairs, but the focus was on policy
analysis and uh and I I got lucky a
couple of times. My career took off.
Then I got a little bored after a couple
of overseas tours. I was tired of
analysis. I switched I made a very
unusual switch to counterterrorism
operations. After 911, I became the
chief of CIA counterterrorism operations
in Pakistan.
And um
and uh then I finished off my career
first as the executive assistant to the
CIA's deputy director for operations and
then um as the counterterrorism officer
at the United Nations.
>> Wow. Yeah. What a what a story to get to
[laughter] the CIA. Well, but and even
before you ask me a question, I have to
say in your intro, you cut right to the
heart of what every single one of us
goes through. There are so many
parallels between what CIA officers go
through and what what military, you
know, our our war fighters go through.
And so often it's either overlooked or
it's out and out ignored.
>> Yeah.
>> And then we end up suffering for the
rest of our lives. Yep. You know, um, a
lot of a lot of people don't realize
this and and I've never talked about it
on on my show. Um, I did 10 years in the
the special ops community and and I'm
going to tell you something. When those
uh intelligence guys um find out that
the information they got was bad and
somebody potentially could have even got
hurt, they don't even have to get hurt.
Just it could have happened.
>> Yeah.
>> They take it serious.
>> Oh, yeah. I mean, it sticks with them
and and you know, in my unit, we've lost
people and and I know for a fact, um I
won't say names or anything, but I do
know for a fact there's a person that
still lives with that um to this day
about uh um the people we've lost and
and they take it serious. Um
>> Oh, yeah. They do.
>> PTSD and trauma and everything doesn't
necessarily mean you had to be on the
battlefield pulling triggers. You know,
it it takes everybody all the way around
to to make us the the fighting force
that we are.
>> Absolutely true. You know, one of my
best friends before we started
recording, you and I were talking about
um where you've served and and you
mentioned Bosnia, Iraq, and Afghanistan.
Well, my best friend from high school uh
joined the military as soon as we
graduated from high school, and he ended
up making full colonel over the course
of a of a long career.
Uh he he ended up with a college degree
in environmental science. So they made
him they put him in charge of the of the
burn pits in both Iraq and Bosnia. And
we used to jokingly call him the garbage
king of of Iraq.
>> But
those burn pits gave him a very rare
brain cancer, a glyopblast, and he died
at 46 years old. His dad was a veteran
of the Second World War and he just
passed away. He was almost a hundred
years old. But he told me
two, three years ago that not a single
night went by that he he didn't have a
nightmare about being on the battlefield
in Belgium or in France in 1942
and wake up screaming. 1942.
That's how long lasting this PTSD was.
And they didn't know, they didn't call
it PTSD back then. They called it shell
shock.
>> Yep.
>> But this poor guy never had a a real
night's sleep for the rest of his life.
>> No. I I you know, at the end of the day,
back then, they they they put a label on
it, but they didn't treat it. There was
there was no
>> no help, no treatment. Um even the
stigma about mental health back then was
>> was similar to what it is today. It was
frowned upon.
>> Yes.
>> And you know, I watched the units as as
I as I was getting out and uh
>> you know, I never admitted I was having
issues, but all the way up to the point
where I was getting out, I was already
thinking about taking my life and I
hadn't even retired yet.
>> And uh I watched because the things that
the the military did for us was
literally check the block type stuff.
you know, they brought in civilian
counselors and they said, "Hey, nobody
will ever know that you talk to them.
They don't talk to the chain of command.
Um, if you're having problems, go see
them." But then they put their office
right next to the commander's office.
[sighs]
>> So, I mean, [laughter]
nobody went I mean, that was the easiest
job you could have because you had no
customers, you know?
>> Well, you know what? We had a similar
situation at the CIA when I first
joined. Uh my boss was walking me around
the old headquarters and then the new
headquarters building and he was
pointing out, you know, that's where the
cafeteria is, that's where the office of
medical services is. And in the uh lobby
of the new headquarters building,
there's like a glass enclosed atrium.
And he said that's where you go if you
want to buy baseball tickets or football
tickets or, you know, you have questions
about your insurance or what. And they
have different windows, you know, sports
tickets and insurance. And then at the
end there was a window for,
you know, if you needed to talk to a
counselor, you had some PTSD, you know,
there's something that's bothering you.
He said, "Let me give you some friendly
advice. Don't ever go to that window."
And I said, "Why not? If it's supposed
to be, you know, to help you." And he
said, "Because at the CIA,
that office that's been set up to help
people falls under the deputy director
for counterintelligence,
not medical."
>> Oh, wow.
>> Counter intelligence. And he said,
"They're going to freeze your career and
then they're going to throw you out."
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. It's it's terrible.
>> You know, uh I I watched it happen
multiple times. uh soldiers um say that
they're going to take their life and and
we put them on suicide watch and and
they literally will force soldiers to
keep 24-hour guard on them knowing that
it it pisses them off because now all
weekend long we've got guard duty on
somebody and and the way they're treated
afterwards is over with. you're now a
dirt bag and and any detail or anything
that comes up, you're going on it. And
>> it it it is not a fortunate thing. So,
you know, we talked about you uh um
getting there and and the amazing
vacation spots you got to go to like
Pakistan [laughter]
and Iraq. But uh you know um what what
was the environment like the inside in
inside the CIA uh immediately following
911? Did did like the world just changed
for you guys?
>> Oh my god. It couldn't have changed any
more than it did and and I I can
encapsulate it in into three words. The
morning that I was leaving for Pakistan,
my boss came up to me and shook my hand
because we knew what we were getting
into. you know, our our chief had had
given us this speech saying, "We're at
war. We all have to fight. Not all of us
are coming home. Go with God." My my
boss came up to me and he shook my hand
and he says, "Kill them all."
And I said I said, "Really, John? We've
gotten to that point already?"
And he just looks at me and he says it
again, "Kill them all."
And so I I went to the airport and I was
determined not to kill them all. to do,
you know, the best as I could. My job
was to capture these guys, not to kill
them.
>> Um, you know, that was another that was
another office that did that. So, uh,
yeah, I did my best, but it it changed
everything. And not not only did it
change everything, it changed everything
permanently. Um, the deputy director for
operations for whom I worked was fond of
saying that that the job of the CIA was
actually very simple. The job of the CIA
was to recruit spies to steal secrets
and then to analyze those secrets to
allow the policymaker to make the best
informed policy.
>> Y
>> after 9/11, the CIA became a
paramilitary organization whose job it
was to kill, capture, and render anyone
who could pose a threat to the United
States.
>> Wow. Mhm.
>> Yeah, I did. I I I knew very little
about the CIA's role. I obviously, you
know, was in the same compounds where
there was all sorts of different forces,
you know, and uh I obviously I didn't
know what they did. They came, they
went, you know, they they hop on our
aircrafts and leave and we pick them up
later and bring them back. And
>> and that was uh the way it is. But what
I can say is it's not like James Bond.
It isn't like what you see on TV.
>> No.
>> The the roles they play, especially all
the way down to our SCOPS teams at a at
a much smaller scale, are are doing real
similar things. Like you said, the the
idea is to recruit somebody. um whether
that be uh pictures that you've taken,
shaken their hand, which could be
nothing more than an introduction, but
now it looks like they're working with
you and threats and stuff like that to
to be done. Those same things are used
against our our soldiers. Those same
things happen on our soil in a bar in
America and and there's, you know, court
cases out there where people have gotten
caught. You can you can see it for
yourself. It's not secrets, but uh um
those things are hard to come back from
and and so when you get over there, how
how is it that that you start setting up
and and figuring out okay, what is the
best way? Because I mean Pakistan has a
border if you call it a border, but you
really you can walk across at any point.
>> Yes. So
>> that's what made this whole war on
terrorism so difficult was trying to
control a country that had no borders.
>> And remember those borders were drawn by
the British.
>> Yeah.
>> And they didn't consult anybody. They
just did it in London with a pen and
just going down the the map. So you're
you're exactly right. It's it's
exceedingly difficult. what I did when I
first got to Pakistan, like literally I
I had been in Pakistan for four hours
and I I go to the station chief uh to
introduce myself and tell him, you know,
that I've arrived and the first thing he
said to me was that he wanted me to come
up with a standard operating procedure
for taking down an al-Qaeda safe house.
>> Okay.
>> So, I had had all the training and then
I I did the advanced training. We called
it um advanced counterterrorism
operations. I had advanced
counterterrorist driving. I had desert
driving. And we I did everything the CIA
had to offer. I had taken it. Weapons,
every kind of weapon. And so I sat down
at my desk with a legal pad and I
thought, well, I'm going to walk through
this. What do I need to do? So I wrote
0200 at the top of the paper because I
would want it to be dark. I would want
everybody to be asleep. uh because the
element of surprise was so important.
And then I wrote a list of things I
needed. I needed extra weapons,
ammunition, encrypted comms, uh
walkietalkies, battering rams, night
vision goggles, all kinds of stuff. I
went on to galls.com, which is a police
supply house in uh Kentucky. bought
$50,000 worth of stuff, put it on my CIA
uh uh credit card, and about a week
later, it all arrived in station. So,
administratively 911, this was so soon
after 911 that 911 was still an open
criminal investigation. So, you had to
bring the FBI in. We had a small FBI
contingent in Islamabads. We would bring
one or two of them on. And of course you
are in Pakistan and it's the Pakistanis
country so you of course have to invite
them.
>> Yeah.
>> Um and we got a tip that there was an
al-Qaeda safe house there in Islamabad.
So we said okay let's give this a try
just see how it works out. 0200 we bust
down the door with the battering ram and
we grabbed these two kids. Two Tunisian
kids both 18 years old. They both burst
into tears.
>> Yeah. And one of them asked me if he
could call his mom
>> to tell him that he had been captured.
Tell her that he had been captured. I
said, "No, you can't call your mom."
>> So, we just took him to the jail.
And I remember saying to the guys,
"Well, that was remarkably easy." Okay?
You know, we got the bulletproof vest
and all geared up and it was easy. And
so another thing that I had done when I
first arrived is I I went to the other
friendly countries uh embassies to
introduce myself as the CIA
counterterrorism chief. And so I said to
to each of them, if you have any
addresses,
lay them on me. We can hit them jointly
or we can do it on our own, whatever you
want. So sure enough, I got a call from
a friendly Arab intelligence uh station
chief. He was kind of a dandy, you know,
he never wanted to get his hands dirty,
but he was perfectly happy to give us
the information so we could get our
hands dirty.
>> Yeah. Sounds like
>> Yeah. Yeah. That that uh
environment.
>> Yeah.
>> Yes. They're the same way, you know, we
are neutral.
>> Yeah. Right. Which means they just pay
everybody.
>> Correct. So um so we broke down that
door a week later and we actually caught
some serious people. We caught a member
of Egyptian Islamic Jihad which of
course had merged with al-Qaeda in 1995.
But before that they had killed
President Sadat in a you know globally
televised assassination during a
military parade. So, this was a big
catch. And uh and we caught a couple of
other mid-level al-Qaeda people. And we
started doing this, you know, on the
regular. Several times a week, we would
hit a hit a safe house and and grab
people. And that that continued until
March of 2002 when we did a major raid,
13 sites simultaneously. And we caught
Abu Zubeda. We caught the commanders of
both the um the Daruna camp and the um
Kandahar camp and uh and dozens and
dozens of other people. So it it went
very well for us.
>> Yeah. Well, you answered a question that
I never knew the answer to before. Um
you know, when I was over there, I had
seen FBI agents, too, and it really
didn't make sense to me.
>> Yeah. Like, why are they why are they
here?
>> Yeah. It it I was just kind of like
standing there looking at him for a
second like man I guess they brought in
everybody.
[laughter]
You know
almost everywhere I served overseas
almost had an FBI presence.
>> Yeah. But normally the FBI presence was
there to catch, you know, the American
who's laundering money in that country
or the American who's not paying his
taxes or the American who's doing child
porn.
>> Yeah.
>> For FBI agents to go on nightly, you
know, counterterrorism raids,
that was highly unusual and
uncomfortable for everybody.
>> Yeah. I mean, 20 year career, that was
the only time that I've ever even seen
them on deployments was was after 911.
>> That was it.
>> So, it it definitely uh it definitely
changed the uh the world for us.
>> And you know, I worked in one huge
station. It had I don't know 50 60
people
>> and the FBI contingent was three agents
and a secretary. So, that kind of gives
you an idea of how unusual it is for the
FBI to be overseas.
>> Yeah. So, you know, I I think you
learned uh something real quick on that
that house that you took down. You know,
the enemy isn't always what we we
picture the enemy to be.
>> I said to my colleagues that night, I
said, "This is the fearsome al-Qaeda.
This is what we're so so so scared of.
This is this is a child."
>> Yeah. Yeah, these guys are children.
>> Yeah.
>> Now, of course, you know, we we weren't
talking about Bin Laden and Zoahi in
that conversation, but for the most
part, Yeah. that's what that's why they
fell apart so quickly.
>> Yeah.
>> They were just children.
>> Yep. They they they were forced
soldiers. That's, you know, they were
>> they were abducted, taken, maybe they
were orphaned from
>> parents dying or whatever. and they were
put in camps and and taught to fight and
and
>> that's it
>> a a cause
>> and you let me add something um almost
to a man they told the same story these
kids they said that I mean they were
generally 18 19 20 years old
>> they couldn't read or write
>> they were from isolated villages in
whatever countries they came from
um had no job training or job skills and
no jobs.
>> Yeah.
>> And and they wanted to get married,
right? They were at marriage age. But
what man would want his daughter to
marry this kid who can't read, can't
write, can't work, and is probably going
to beat up his daughter?
>> Yeah.
>> And so the local imam from the village
would go to these kids and say, "What
are you doing here? Why do why do you
want to stay in in this village? You
should go to Afghanistan and make jihad
against the Americans, and we'll give
you $300 a month. and if you're martyed,
we'll give your parents $500 martyrdom
bonus. And they said, "Okay." These guys
couldn't find the United States on a
map. They had never read the Quran. They
didn't know anything about US foreign
policy. They were thinking, " $300 a
month? It usually takes my dad a year to
earn $300."
>> Yeah.
Yeah. It's it is uh um
not a a good picture, you know. Yeah.
>> When when when civilians hear us talk
about how children are are used as
shields and and everything else,
>> I it's one thing to say it, it's another
thing to see it.
>> Yeah, you can say that again.
>> It affects you completely different. So,
let's get into
kind of where we discover about the
torture and and stuff. So, Abu Zubayada,
I know I said his name, his last name
wrong.
>> Zuba.
>> Zuba. Okay. And the the torture program.
Yeah. How how did this all come about?
Because I mean, this was a a pretty uh
high target. We're no longer talking
about kids anymore.
>> Yeah. We we believed at the time that
Abu Zuba was the number three in
al-Qaeda. That turned out to not be
true. He was working with al-Qaeda, but
he had never joined al-Qaeda and he had
never pledged feelalty to Osama bin
Laden. But Abisa was sort of a an
al-Qaeda fixer. If you wanted to start
fighting, he would get you into
Afghanistan. If you were tired of the
fight and you wanted to go home, he
would get you out, get a fake passport,
and get you back to your home country.
He founded the House of Martyrs, the the
al-Qaeda safe house in Peshawar,
Pakistan. He founded the two training
camps in Kandahar and in Helman
province. So, he was a bad guy. He he
did a lot for al-Qaeda.
>> Mhm.
>> Um but he was not the number three. And
uh
[sighs]
in the months leading up to the capture,
he was captured in March of 2002.
CIA headquarters, the leadership at CIA
was preparing for what to do once we
caught one of the top three or four and
they were convinced to adopt this
so-called enhanced interrogation program
which was really a reverse engineered
SER program.
>> Okay,
>> that you know we've always acknowledged
as as torture. And and keep in mind we
had actual laws on the books that
forbade us from doing exactly the
techniques that the enhanced
interrogations uh called for.
>> Yeah.
>> So
there were two contract psychologists um
uh James Mitchell and Bruce Jessen and
uh they had been contractors with the
Air Force. They reverse engineered Seir,
presented it to George Tennant at the
CIA, were paid $108 million
and um and they flew out to the secret
site. Wizedo was the first HVT highv
value target that we had captured. And
so they sort of experimented on him. But
you know how these things go. They're
cowboys and this is a slippery slope.
and the next thing you know, you're
doing all kinds of things that the
Justice Department never said you could
do
>> and it just got worse from there.
>> You know, I think one of the main
reasons why why it's not recommended is
is it taints the the
um confessions, you know.
>> You bet it does.
>> Not Not only now are you getting the
information you want, but now you don't
even know if it's true. No,
>> because
>> and it's likely not because the prisoner
is telling you anything that he thinks
you want to hear just to get you to stop
torturing him.
>> Yeah. It it it it could become a
situation where it's even more dangerous
because now you're you're acting on this
information that that may or may not be
true and and it it puts operators in a
situation where they're not really 100%
sure what they're going to walk into.
That's exactly right.
>> That's exactly in the meantime, you're
bogging down your analysts
>> with with hundreds or thousands of hours
of garbage that that the prisoner has
given you and this team of analysts that
could be doing important work is sorting
through all this trash trying to figure
out what's true and what's not true.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And and again, it's it's
tough, you know, um if you don't have
reliable sources, you know, it's much
better. I I think the interpreters
programs was was much better where by
being a interpreter it it eventually
could lead to you having a life in
America and uh that motivation was a lot
more effective than I think uh you know
torturing people. So
>> oh my god I agree. How uh if if you can
talk about it, how did how did you
discover all of this was was happening?
Because I assume once the target was
captured, they were turned over to
another team.
>> Yes.
>> And put in a a prison behind 800 walls.
>> Correct. Correct. So, um
when my tour ended in is Islamabad,
[clears throat]
I went back to CIA headquarters. I
became the chief of counter intelligence
uh for the Osama bin Laden unit called
Alex Station. And uh I was in the
cafeteria one day and a colleague of
mine came up to me and said that he was
glad he ran into me and uh would I like
to be certified in the use of enhanced
interrogation techniques. And I had
never heard the term before. So he
explained to me what this meant and I
said, "Man, that sounds like a torture
program. What are you talking about?"
>> And he said, "No, the ju the uh the um
Department of Justice signed off on it
and the president approved it. It's not
torture." I said, "Ah, let me think
about it for an hour." So, I went up to
the seventh floor, the executive floor
of the CIA. There was a senior, very
senior um officer there for whom I had
worked 10 years earlier in the Middle
East. And uh I went in and asked his
advice and he told me to run screaming
from the room that this was a torture
program. It was going to be a slippery
slope right to prison and just get away
from it. And so I declined. But then
because I had captured Abuzu Beta, I got
promoted and bumped up to be the
executive assistant to the deputy
director for operations. And in that
position, I saw literally everything
that the CIA was doing around the world.
>> Wow.
>> And that was just when the torture the
actual torture sessions began.
>> Wow. So So yeah, your your eyes now get
opened up like like you're the brand new
guy again. Yeah, you're
>> coming in and seeing things that that
doors are opening that you never even
knew existed.
>> Oh, I'll tell you. I had an old friend
from analysis who asked me, "So, so how
is it up there on the seventh floor?" I
said, "It is the most fascinating job
I've ever had in my life." And he said,
"But don't you feel bad that you're not
making a contribution like you used to
in analysis?"
And I said, "Buddy, you don't have the
foggiest idea what you're talking
about."
>> Wow. Yeah.
>> Yeah. I mean all all agencies like this
I you know and I I would say even all
the way down to special ops and military
they work off of a siloed type uh
system.
>> Absolutely.
>> You know there's a reason why they've
added in that part of the the documents.
Not only do you have to have the
clearance but a need to know that
information as well. You know just
because you you have a clearance high
enough to read something but have no
need doesn't mean you get access. And I
think that happens a lot even in our
world. You know, I I was at the very low
level. I was with the 160th and uh you
know, I couldn't tell you half the stuff
that other
>> No.
>> departments was doing.
>> No. And it's the same at the CIA. I
don't have the foggiest idea what the
guy next to me is doing. I I wrote in my
first book when when we turned over
Abazuba to the rendition team.
>> Um one of the guys on the plane uh was a
friend of mine
>> and uh so you know it's 4:00 in the
morning and and the plane lands and
we're loading up onto the plane and he
said so who's your prisoner? And I said
oh man I'm so sorry but you don't have a
you don't have a need to know. And he
said no no that's cool. And I said where
are you taking him? And he said, "Oh,
dude, I'm sorry, but you don't have a
need to know." And I said, "Yeah, of
course you're right. I don't."
>> Yeah.
>> And so that was it because my job was to
catch him and put him on the plane. And
the other guy's job was to fly the plane
from point A to point B. And that was
it.
>> Yeah.
>> Don't ask questions.
>> Yeah. And and as as we're going to get
into it, you know, the asking questions
can lead you into to areas that that
you're not sure you wanted to be in.
>> Got that right.
>> So, let's get into the the
whistleblowing. Um, so now you're you're
you're got a penthouse view of of the
CIA and and you see this stuff going on.
Um, what led you to deciding
I've got to say something? [gasps]
>> I objected from the get-go. They asked
14 people uh to be to go through the
training to torture these guys. And I'm
I'm sorry to say that I was the only one
who said no. Um, and it's not just that
I had a a moral problem with it. I
believe strongly and correctly in
retrospect that it was just simply
illegal.
>> Mhm.
>> So in the intervening years, I've done a
lot of research into this. I like to
think that I'm, you know, one of the
country's leading experts on this very
narrow issue. We have a law in this
country called the Federal Torture Act
of 1946.
And it specifically bans
exactly those techniques that we were
using. We executed Japanese soldiers in
1945 for waterboarding American PS. That
was a death penalty crime to waterboard
somebody. And then in January of 1968, I
believe it was January the 11th, the
Washington Post ran a front page photo
of an American soldier waterboarding a
Vietnamese P.
And
the Secretary of Defense, Robert
McNamera, ordered an investigation the
minute he saw this picture. That soldier
was arrested. He was convicted of
torture and he was sentenced to 20 years
at Levvenworth.
>> Yeah.
>> And then in 2002, like magic, it's all
legal. But the truth is, the law never
changed. Congress never amended that
law.
>> Yeah.
We just decided it just didn't fit where
we wanted to be in 2002 and we just
pretended that the law didn't exist.
Well, that's not a constitutional
democracy.
>> No.
>> If you want to be pro torture, then go
on the record and change the law
and they just didn't bother to do that.
>> Yeah. Well, it it would have took too
much time. Yeah. You know, and and too
much work and
>> and when you create this scenario where
the like you said, the president signed
off on it. So, it's it's good to go.
Now, in a court, you've got the
president that says basically said, "No,
we're not going to do it." And yes, we
are going to do it. And and it kind of
gives the the people that are
responsible for it a a escape.
>> Yes. Yes. Exactly. Exactly. Right. And
you know the the sad truth too is that
um all these guys who were at the top
positions at the CIA in this period,
they all went on to multi-million dollar
book deals and positions on the board of
directors of of a dozen different uh
defense contractors. They all got rich.
Nobody was prosecuted. Everybody got
rich. [clears throat]
>> Wow.
I it is I I keep going back to it
because I know the the Marines that was
at that uh prison um camp. Now, it's not
the exact same scenario. You know, they
they were they were torturing people for
the the thrill of torturing people, not
>> not trying to get information because
they were just guards as
>> You're right. They were.
>> That's right.
>> But they were prosecuted and and they
they're doing some serious time.
>> Yes. Yes. You're exactly right. But why
then [clears throat]
>> should we have this two-tier justice
system?
>> Yeah.
>> I think in today's age uh that's on a
lot of people's uh uh minds when it when
they they talk about politics. I think
it's definitely like a you know what
shoes do you wear and they pertain to
you in this way.
>> It really it really is.
>> That's right.
How is it that you know uh Congress
especially I mean they they want
whistleblowers. I mean now we've got
whistleblowers for UFOs and and
everything else.
>> IRS.
>> Yeah. IRS
>> department.
>> Absolutely. So how is it that uh um
after after you divulge this and it
obviously turned out to be not correctly
done right. It was supposed to have been
no torture type scenarios. How how did
it come back to bite you? I had a very
powerful enemy in John Brennan. Uh I've
known John for 35 years. We've hated
each other for 35 years. And he was uh
Barack Obama's deputy national security
adviser for counterterrorism. He was one
of the godfathers of the torture
program. He went on to be the CIA
director and he demanded that I be
prosecuted. Um, that's where that came
from. On Capitol Hill, it's much better
now. It was it was chaos up there when I
was being prosecuted. But a couple of
people have come forward as sort of the
go-to protectors of whistleblowers. The
most important of whom is um is um Iowa
Senator um
I'm having a mental blank. Chuck
Grassley. Iowa Senator Chuck Grassley.
Now, Grassley is very old. He's 94, 95
years old, but he's the one guy that you
can expect support from. Another one on
the House side is Jim Jordan, uh, the
congressman from Ohio. He's chairman of
the Judiciary Committee. He's more
politicized on this issue, but he is a
friend of whistleblowers. Um, Ran Paul,
the senator from Kentucky, is another
one. And, um, there's a Democrat, Ron
Weiden, senator from Oregon. And that's
pretty much it.
>> Yeah.
>> Now, there are 435 members of the House
of Representatives. There are 100
senators. We're talking about 535
people, and we can name four who support
whistleblowers.
>> Wow.
>> So, so it's still an uphill struggle,
but at least it's better than it was 10
years ago,
>> man. You know, that's that's not
encouraging stats to get people to want
to come forward. That is that is
absolutely for sure.
>> So, no.
Now, now it comes out. We know that uh
you were being prosecuted over uh uh
vengeance, you know, more than anything.
Um
and and it ended up costing you your
career and and the fact that you had to
go to prison for this. Um,
>> yeah,
>> I believe I read in one of your bios
that you'd said that the CIA training
had kind of helped you make it through
uh your time behind the the walls. How
how so?
>> Well, at sentencing, my attorneys asked
the judge to send me to a minimum
security work camp.
>> Okay.
>> Minimum security um has no bars on the
windows. The doors aren't locked. You're
free to come and go as you please.
You're just on your honor not to abscond
and run away.
>> And so the camps are always situated
next to a higher security prison because
when there's a riot, then the guys in
the camp go into the prison to do the
laundry and do the cooking and stuff
like that. The Justice Department had no
objection to a minimum security work
camp.
The CIA did, however,
>> and so when I arrived at the prison
thinking I was going to the camp, they
put me into the actual prison instead.
>> So, it took me about four or five days
before I got access to a phone. And
finally, I was able to call my lawyers
and I I told them, "Hey, they put me in
the actual prison with the mafia dons
and the drug kingpins and the
pedophiles. So, what do I do?" And my
attorney said, 'Oh my god. Well, we can
file a motion, but it'll be two years
before we get a hearing and you'll be
home by then. He said, 'I' buddy. You're
just going to have to tough it out.
>> Oh wow.
>> And so I thought to myself, you've lived
in worse places than Lorettto,
Pennsylvania.
And I decided to rely on my CIA training
to make sure that I stayed safe and
stayed at the top of the social heap. So
the first thing I started doing is to
form strategic alliances and my first
alliance
uh was with the Aryans followed closely
by the Italians
and um knock on wood I didn't have one
single day of trouble.
>> Wow. Yeah. We have one of those uh um
minimum security and and a a not minimum
security in in my hometown there Jessup
Georgia. Oh, sure.
>> Federal and and uh believe it or not,
the majority of the people that that get
taken out of the minimum security isn't
because they got caught breaking out.
It's because they got caught breaking
back in. You know, they they
>> Exactly. Right.
>> they snuck out to go see a girl or
>> That's right. or get a pizza or pick up
a cell phone. Man, that happened almost
every day. Like you you've worked your
way down in security to a minimum and
you're going to throw it away by
sneaking into the woods to meet up with
your girlfriend.
>> Yep.
>> Or to order a pizza.
>> Yeah.
>> I never understood that.
>> Yeah. Me neither. But uh it it
definitely happened all the time.
>> So that kind of shocked me that you
said, you know, the first connection you
made was was with the the Aryans. You
know,
>> I had been in prison for I don't know,
less than an hour.
>> And these two Aryans came into my cell
and I jumped up. I put up my dukes. I
got to defend myself, but I thought I'm
going to get my ass kicked. It's two of
them and one of me and one of them said,
"Take it easy. Are you the new guy?" I
said, "Yeah." So, he says, "Uh, are you
a fag?" I said, "No, I'm not a fag." And
he says, "Uh, are you a a rat?" And I
said, "No, I'm not a rat. I didn't have
anybody else in my case." And he said,
"Are you a chomo?" I said, "I don't know
what that means." He goes, "Chomo, child
molester." I said, "No, I'm not a child
molester." And he says, "Okay, uh, you
can sit with the Aryans in the
cafeteria." And I was like, "Oh, okay."
So finally one of the Italians,
actually the number three in the Banano
family,
>> came up to me. He he lived across the
hall from me and he said, ' Let me ask
you a question. He said, 'Why do you sit
with those Nazi retards in the
cafeteria?
I said, I don't know. My my first day
here, they told me to sit with them. And
he says, from today, you're with the
Italians.
And so for the rest of my sentence, I
sat with the Italians every day.
>> Yeah. I think it, you know, it comes
down to numbers. You know, the the Aryan
nations are is not the majority,
>> right?
>> And uh I would imagine neither are the
Italians. And uh so I it does make sense
in that aspect. Um
>> but usually the the Aryan nation, you
would think that they're they're they
had to have known that you were not um
in a gang. I mean,
>> yeah,
>> you don't look like the kind of guy
that's just covered in tattoos and
>> I I don't have any. No, no, that's
that's a good that's a good point and a
good observation. So, the Aryan table,
the cafeteria is very very strictly
segregated.
>> So, there's a dividing line right down
the middle and the entire one side is
black guys
>> and they tend to not segregate like the
whites do. The whites are very clearly
divided. the blacks. If you're black,
you're in. They don't care if you're a
pedophile, a drug dealer. They don't
care what you did. You're you're in.
>> On the on the white side of the
cafeteria, the first table, the first
set of tables is the the the
aryens. Some some people didn't call it
the aryens. They called it the good
guys.
>> Oh, okay.
>> Good. Good meaning that your paper was
good. So, you're not a rat or a uh or a
pedophile. And so half like a table and
a half are actual Aryan Brotherhood and
then a table and a half are good guys
who are not members of the Aryan
Brotherhood. The next table, the next
set of three tables,
one table is Italians, one table is
Native Americans, and one table is sort
of overflow for the Aryans if you can't
all fit in that front row. And then
behind them are three groups of three
tables each. And that's where all the
pedophiles and the rats and the gays
sit.
>> Gotcha. So I I'm assuming, you know,
your cover was kept while you were in
there then that that you you didn't work
for the CIA. You didn't uh
>> No, sir.
>> No.
>> My case was on the front page of the New
York Times and the Washington Post. It
was on TV all the time. And so there was
one Italian who not only became my best
friend in prison, but here we are 10
years later and is still one of my best
friends in the world. He took it upon
himself out of the kindness of his
heart. After reading an article in the
New York Times saying, "I was coming in
4 days to that prison." He went to every
one of the Italians, the senior, the
leadership people to say, "There's this
guy coming on Thursday. He's a CIA guy,
but there's a difference between the CIA
and the FBI. The FBI is cops.
>> Yep.
>> The CIA protects us from the Muslims.
And this guy hates the FBI as much as we
do. And so open arms when I arrived.
They welcomed me
>> and and he saved me more trouble than I
could even calculate. I'm deeply
indebted to him. He's such a such a
sweet guy. And then I'm proud to say he
was serving at first he was serving
triple life without parole for a first
time nonviolent drug offense.
>> Wow.
>> He appealed and they cut it to 30 years.
First time nonviolent drug offense. And
then I wrote an appeal for him
and uh and the Justice Department agreed
to hear to to to oppose the appeal but
to allow a judge to hear it and he won.
And so he was released a year after I
was. So he I say to him, I owe him so
much. And he says, no, I owe you so
much. And his mother is like crying and
hugging me every time we get together.
And it's like, no, I love you. No, I
love you. And
>> yeah, real friend. true friend.
>> That's that's you know prison is is
another form of trauma and trauma does
build bonds.
>> I read I read in a book called uh the
sociopath next door
>> that 85%
of the people in prison at any level
whether and it whether it's federal,
state or local 85%
have a diagnosible mental illness.
I Yeah, I would agree.
>> Stunning.
>> Yeah, those numbers are are extremely
close within our our homeless as well.
>> Oh, that I'm I'm sure that that's true.
I'm sure that And I'll tell you what,
there are a lot of homeless people who
commit crimes just so they can go to
prison and spend the winter indoors. One
of my cellmates was a guy from uh
Pittsburgh. He was living in a cardboard
box under a bridge in Pittsburgh. And he
said as soon as it started to get cold,
he violated parole on purpose because he
says, "Look, I don't want to winter's
tough in Pittsburgh. I'm from near
Pittsburgh." So, he didn't want to spend
the winter in that cardboard box. And he
says, "Look, I got a warm bed. I got
three meals a day. I have medical care,
free medicine. Yeah.
>> So, he violated parole. They gave him
six months. He says, "Great." They let
him out in the spring. Everybody's
happy.
>> Yep. Yeah.
>> That's not That's not the way life
should be.
>> No, it it should not be. And and that's
a you know, and this is for a whole
another show, but I talk about this on
my other podcast as well. This is why
the the VA can't get a grasp around um
homelessness and mental health. Yeah.
both problems are are combined and
there's a lot of little uh symptoms that
bleed off onto this.
>> Yes, indeed.
>> And it's just impossible for one agency
to to be the the jack of all trades.
>> It is it's impossible, especially when
that agency is um underfunded.
>> Yeah. Yep.
>> And corrupt at the same time.
>> Yeah. Oh, yeah. Yeah. As we seen there
with the whole waiting list uh uh
agenda. Absolutely. So you you you do
your time, you you you get out. What was
I mean, it it sounds like almost like
this became a a give and take. You
accomplished a a good thing for America.
>> Thank you.
>> But you gave up, you know, x amount of
years of your life.
>> Yeah. And not just that, I Yeah. I gave
up two years of my life, but uh the
Obama Justice Department seized my
federal pension, so I I'm going to have
to work till the day I die. I have no
pension, nothing. No savings, no
nothing. Um, my wife and I split up. Uh,
I entered into an eight-year battle uh
over custody.
>> Wow.
>> Uh, went bankrupt.
I still owe more than a million dollars
to my attorneys that they'll never see
because I don't have a million dollars.
>> Yeah.
>> And um, you know, just getting a job, it
it's one thing. I'm lucky because I'm
kind of like Washington famous. Mhm.
>> So, people sort of come to me and, you
know, with offers here and there.
>> Yeah.
>> But when I first got out of prison, I
got turned down by by Uber because I'm a
felon,
>> by by uh Door Dash because I'm a felon.
I went to the local grocery stores, they
wouldn't hire me. I applied for a job as
a dishwasher in a diner and they
wouldn't hire me. I I got a job for one
day as a baggage handler at National
Airport. And then they fired me at the
end of my first day because they didn't
realize I was a convicted felon.
So yeah, it's it's freaking hard, let me
tell you.
>> Yeah. And and and what changes came
about from from you uh whistleblowing?
Did the did the program get destroyed?
>> I am so proud
of the of the answer to that question.
So 6 weeks before I I was released, I
called my wife. I was able to call my
wife every other day for 15 minutes and
I said to her, "So how's your day?" She
said, "It's great." I said, "Really
great? Why? Why is it great?" And she
said, "Because the Senate torture report
was released today and it proved that
everything you said was true." And then
John McCain, God bless him, John McCain
stood up on the floor of the Senate and
said that the country owed me a debt of
gratitude because without my
revelations, the American people would
never have known what the government was
doing in their name. And so he sponsored
the McCain Feinstein amendment which
formally and permanently banned torture.
And now it's illegal under any
circumstances.
So, it was worth it.
>> Yeah, that's, you know, that that is
awesome because uh like you said, what
we gave up was, you know, endangering
people's lives that were still over
there fighting. And
>> that's right.
>> You know, people don't understand how
the the smallest amount of OBSAC is that
given away is so powerful, much more
powerful than Absolutely. than a guy
with an M4, you know.
And so I think uh I think people
underestimate
that that stuff the the the power of
conversation over a couple beers.
>> Yes.
>> With the wrong person.
>> It works.
>> It does.
>> It it might take a little bit of time,
but it works.
>> Yep. And and the intel you end up
getting is is so much better, you know.
>> Yeah.
um having leverage because on once you
start you go down that road of torture,
you lose your ability for leverage.
>> That's it.
>> You've now put the person in a desperate
situation who feels I have nothing to
lose. I'm going to die if I say nothing.
And if they find out it's a lie, I'll
die too. But
>> yes,
>> I stand a chance of living for a longer
period if I lie.
>> That's right. That's right. It's true.
>> Yeah. It is it is a a brutal slope to go
down.
So,
whistleblowers
and protection and ethics, right? So,
what advice if if if somebody was to
come out today and say, "Hey, I'm I'm
thinking about coming forward with
this." Yeah. And and there may be some
repercussions. What advice would you
give them?
>> Oh, I'm so glad you asked that. Hire an
attorney before you say a single word. I
made a critical mistake by blowing the
whistle and then hiring an attorney
because I had to be reactive to
everything. You want to be proactive.
>> So, don't blow the whistle unless your
attorney is sitting in the seat next to
you and is able to advise you.
>> Yeah. Yeah. That that makes a lot of
sense. But but again, I I you know, on
on your behalf coming forward, you know,
you had two things against you. one, you
you probably didn't ever anticipate that
what you're going to be say is going to
be held against you, you know, because
you wasn't the the
uh inalent here. You weren't the the
person being targeted. You were you were
the person coming forward. So why would
you think that right anything you say is
going to be held against you?
>> Yes. And
>> the second the second part of that is is
every day longer that you don't say
something, somebody's being tortured.
That's exactly right.
>> You know, so it's not like you you had
the the ability of time. You know, we
probably have a little bit more time
before the UFOs come. So those guys
probably have time to get attorneys and
>> Yeah, that's right.
>> the [laughter] right thing.
>> That's right.
>> So,
so with that being said, there is areas
in the government, right, that that a
lot of people uh um talk about, you
know, one being the deep state. Yes. you
know, do you do you believe that to be
true? Because that's part of what comes
out of uh the the whole UFO
whistleblowers.
>> Oh, yeah. I I do. I do. Um we don't have
to call it the deep state. We can call
it the federal bureaucracy. But yeah,
there's there's an entire, you know,
there's an entire subculture in
government that's there for 30, 35, in
some cases 40 years. They can outweight
presidents. They're not going anywhere
because of the Civil Service Act. You
can't fire them.
>> Yeah.
>> So, yeah. If they don't like a
president, they just ignore him because
they know in four years or eight years,
he's going to be gone and somebody else
is going to be in.
>> Yeah. And and truth be said, you know,
the power is in the Congress, the Senate
more than it is the president, you know.
>> That's right.
>> So, if you're friends with them on that
side, you probably stand a pretty good
chance to survive the next four years.
>> That's right.
>> So, yeah.
you know, this is really a an amazing
story. You know,
>> it's been a long road.
>> I I can imagine, you know, I I I can't
imagine the things that you went through
>> um dealing with the just the the normal
effects of combat. Yeah.
>> On top of dealing with
>> the the people that you were serving
>> coming against you, you know, I mean,
this is trauma on top of trauma.
>> It is.
>> Yeah.
>> It is indeed. It's tough. it it don't
you know I again we're talking about a
major we're not talking about a a local
employer so we're talking about a major
agency it's not like there's any
recourse that that you're going to stand
a chance without just throwing yourself
more in debt and and and probably
nothing good come out of it anyways
>> that's right
>> so I do I I feel for you in that in that
side we uh um
I know we're getting to top I got just a
couple more things. So, your your career
goes
this this time frame and it and it ends
um horribly, right?
>> Mhm.
>> Do you have any resentment or regrets
other than wishing you would have got an
attorney to begin with? Is there
anything that uh
>> No, you regret.
>> No, no, no regrets at all. You know
what? You'll make yourself crazy if you
think about regrets.
>> I agree. And so, no, I I don't even
think about it. Like, I'm I seriously
don't ever think about it. You just have
to look to the future and keep pushing
uh in the right direction moving
forward. So, now, you know, I write
books. I I my eighth book is coming out
in the next several weeks. I'm working
on I've got a contract for four more
after this. Um, I I speak, I teach at
universities, and uh,
>> yeah, uh, you know, I I'm 60 years old
now, and I try to do what is fun, what's
going to help me pay the bills for the
next, uh, month or so.
And, uh, yeah, you have to look to the
future. You have to, you'll drive
yourself crazy if you don't.
>> I I completely agree. You know, it's
it's it is weird. You know, the Lord
gives us strength but no brains. And
then as we get older, we lose our
strength, but we gain the wisdom. And
>> and it it is it is amazing how he knows
that if I put the two together at the
same time, how dangerous it can be.
>> That's right.
>> And so I think I think it's it's really
important that that once you people
realize that that path that you're on
isn't about regret.
>> It's it's the path that's taking you to
putting you where you're supposed to be.
And you'll find that when you get there,
>> you know, this is not the way I
envisioned my life working out.
>> Oh, I'm sure.
>> But
I I I had to come to the conclusion that
this is what I was meant to do. And so I
embrace it.
>> Yep.
>> I do.
>> Yeah. You know, I I'm like I said, I'm
retired. So, um I'm I'm happier now than
I ever was when I owned my trucking
company and and was making great money,
you know. There you go.
>> And I'm helping veterans every day. I
run a nonprofit and uh I got a very
small little media company that that
helps people with their podcast.
>> There you go. Here, if you can see
behind me, I've got my dad.
>> Oh, you muted yourself.
>> Sorry. I've got
>> I've got my dad's flag right up there
for for all to see. I'm very very proud
of him. Absolutely.
>> My family, my extended family has a very
long history in the Marine Corps and
every served proudly. Every last one of
them.
>> Okay. That's, you know, that's another
reason where where this podcast is for.
It's it's about documenting everybody's
story. And I think we all recently
learned we don't know in 30 years what
the history books are going to teach
about us.
>> That's right. and and if you want the
opportunity to tell your side, this is
the time to do it because once it's on
the internet, it's there.
>> It's there forever. That's exactly my
position.
>> Absolutely. My my last question before I
I give you the opportunity to come
forward and and uh tell everybody where
they can get all your books and and
everything.
>> Thank you.
>> If you could go back in time and and
pick a spot where you were in your
darkest moment and you don't have to
talk about the moment, what would be the
advice you would give yourself?
Things really do get better. They really
do. You may be blind to it at that
moment. I had one of those moments. I
was going to do something terrible. And
I think my wife realized just how dark
the time it was. And And so she wouldn't
leave me alone.
>> That's good.
>> But it it really does get better even if
you can't see it at that moment.
Yeah. Yeah. Depression is is is
got the ability to to really just
control what you see and what you,
>> you know, and it's not a it's not an
enemy on enemy on the battlefield that
you can outflank. It's
>> No,
>> it is is something that gains total
control over you.
>> That's it. You can't run from it.
>> Nope. And and no matter what you do,
whether you drown it with alcohol or
drugs or or gambling or sex, whatever
your addictions are, that that stems
from this, it's it's not going to let go
of you until you work through it.
>> Yes. Absolutely right.
>> And that that is a tough that's some
great advice and and I hope a lot of the
listeners will will hear that and be a
part of it as well. Let me bring you
forward and and give everybody the
opportunity to find out where they can
connect with you and and where they can
uh purchase books and and thank you.
>> Well, the books the books are all on
Amazon and uh actually almost all of
them are on Amazon. The first one is out
of print, so I apologize for that. But
um you can find me on Twitter or X John
Kuryaku on Substack. I I post everything
that I do there. Um, also John Kuryaku.
Um, I have a TV show on the Unified
Network. It's unifyd.com.
And, um,
and also a company called Ivycyber. So,
it's ivyscyber.com.
Uh, yeah, everything's out there. My own
website is johncuryaku.com
and it'll just send you wherever you
need to go. Thanks for asking.
>> All right. I will absolutely make sure
uh uh when the the people see this,
we'll get these uh links and everything
up on the screen.
>> Thank you.
>> Uh the books and and I'll also note them
in the the bios and and the descriptions
as well to make it easy for people to to
>> Thank you very much. Appreciate it. Good
to see you.
>> Good to see you, too, John. You you've
got an amazing story and and I'm I'm
glad you was able to connect with us. I
I had a great time. Thank
>> you. Same here. Appreciate you having
me.
>> You too.
>> [music]
[music]
>> You've been listening to History Told
Forward, a podcast from the Barracks
Media Network. Thanks to our guest for
sharing their insight and thank you for
listening. You can find more
conversations like this across the
Barracks Media Network.
We'll see you next